hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and today we are going to
cover a very important topic in spring
board that is Bean so in the previous
four topics we have used couple of times
that this is been this is been but we
will cover in depth today so in a simple
term if I have to Define Bean then I
call it Bean is a Java
object which is managed by a spring
container that is iOS C inversion of
control
container okay so it's no different than
Java object but only managed by Spring
and what is ioc container ioc container
contains all the beans which get created
and also manage them so creation
initialization and complete end to
endend managing their life cycle right
that is done by
ioc okay so how to create a
bean so there are two ways to create a
bean one is through adate component
annotation and another is through at
theate Bean annotation with both ways
you can create a bean but there are some
specific use cases where you have to use
ad theate be annotation using this might
not help you for those use cases okay
and what are those use cases I will tell
you
soon so let's first start with at the
rate component
annotation so at theate component
annotation follows convention over
configuration approach what does it mean
so check this very simple example which
I have created here a very simple class
user with username and email and it's
getter and Setter very basic class and I
have put at theate component at
top now this will tell spring boot hey
you have to create its object you have
to manage its life cycle right so that's
the work of the
component so component is convention
over configuration what does it means so
a spring boot when it try to create an
object of it it uses some Auto
configuration like hey if I have to uh
create its object call it's default
Constructor and then with using that we
can create its object right because we
are not providing any external
configuration that and telling
springboard that how you should create
an user object no we haven't provided
any
configuration at theate component spring
boot automatically use some its
autoconfigure that okay I will use
default Constructor to create its
object okay
at theate controller at theate service
all are internally tell spring to create
bean and manage it because if you see
here atate controller if I am putting so
at theate controller also internally is
nothing but component also right it is
also a
component
similarly service atate repository or
are performing some specific task plus
also they are
component so all telling the spring that
you have to create an object of it and
manage its life
cycle okay so this example is very
simple right but now consider this
example what would happen to this again
same user class but only difference is
now I have created one specific
Constructor
now you know that when we provide our
own
Constructor Java will not add default
Constructor here now default Constructor
is not present here okay
so if I put at theate component means I
am telling spring boot to create its
object now spring boot has it
autoconfigured that okay I have to call
its default Constructor now when when it
will try to create its being when it
will try to create its object will it be
able to create no because there is no
default Constructor here and spring
doesn't know what to pass in the
username and email so when you will try
to start an application your application
will actually fail that not able to
create a
beam so what to do in this
case you have to tell spring boot that
hey when you create a user object pass
this username this email right then only
you would be able to create it because
there is no default Constructor it so
that's where at theate Bean annotation
can
help
right so atate Bean comes into the
picture where we provide the
configuration details so like external
configuration and tells the springboard
to use it while creating a bean so this
is how we do it so here if you see that
first from the user class I have removed
the at theate component now it is not
needed okay the same example where there
is no default Constructor now see this
is how you create a configuration file
so first create a class provide any
name and use this annotation at the rate
configuration at theate configuration
annotation tells the spring boot that
hey in this class you will find certain
Bean methods right for that you have to
create Bean
also right so here we can provide at
theate Bean on a method so you can use
any method name so I've given a name
like create user Bean because I want to
create a user so I just given a name
create user Bean you can provide
anything return type is important so
okay so return type is user it has to
create this
object so now here I'm telling springbot
that how you should create its object so
I'm telling create like this new user
pass this username default username
default
email now what would happen is so
whenever a spring tried to
create an object of this user now it
will not use Auto configuration why
because we have provided the external
configuration now suppose let's say you
can ask me that hey what would happen
Shan if I provide atate component here
also means one way I'm telling uh spring
to use Auto configuration but in the
external configuration also I have
provided the bean and telling spring to
use this now let's say there is
something called default Constructor
also here present so which one it will
use so first priority will goes to this
one you can try it out right uh so you
can create this uh object and after that
try printing system do do do print lent
and you can see which one actually
spring boot uses to
invoke right so this should get first
priority external configuration because
this is what we are providing right and
what we want that is first priority to
Spring boot not Auto
configuration okay so now you understand
like uh there is certain specific use
cases where at theate Bean only can help
you and this is one of the use case
let's say where default Constructor is
not present then you have to
provide the how to create an object
using at theate Bean
annotation so also there is one more uh
question can come that okay what if I
have multiple atate Bean methods where
I'm creating a same user let's say
create user Bean one create user Bean 2
both returning user so what would happen
here so generally in this case what
generally happen is spring boot goes one
by one and create a bean for all so in
this case two object would get
created like Bean
one being two so one get created for
this user also another is another for
this user but with this information
default username default email default
username default email and another is
another
username and another email right and
both now is going to manage by
ioc okay so no matter how many times you
write it a spring boot will create that
many objects for
it and which want to use that we can see
later there are something called at
theate qualifiers right or at theate you
can provide a name to the bean and tell
in your code thaty I even there are
multiple objects I want to use this
specific object that we will see
different
later okay but first concentrate on that
how you can create a bean through atate
component and through ad theate
be so there are further two questions
again comes to our mind that okay sh I
know how to create a bean now right but
how spring boot find these beans because
I have a huge application code base and
there are like thousands of file and I
have written at theate component at
let's say 50 60 files and also I have at
the rate configuration file right where
I have provided at the rate
be so how actually is spring boot able
to find this classes where it has to
create a
beam and another question is at what
time these beans get
created right
so like as soon as you write it does it
created like when Java compiles or what
at what time is beans get created so
that is another question which get
asked so let's first focus on the first
part how spring boot find this Bean so
there are two ways one is at theate
component scan annotation so at theate
component annotation tells a spring boot
to look in a specifi specified package
and subpackage and look for all this
annotated classes like at theate
component atate service atate repository
atate controller as I already told you
that these annotations are also nothing
but component two right so spring boot
will look look for all these annotations
in the specified package and subpackage
and then it able to find those
beans so let's say
this in the in this class a spring boot
application where we have a main you can
write this at theate component scan and
provide a base package now spring boot
goes start from this and further sub
packages so this Plus subpackage and
look for this
annotations now even if you don't
provide this as in the I think starting
video I also tell you that spring boot
application also has atate component
scan internally so if you see that
spring boot
application also has adate component
scan and its Auto configuration is that
start from the package where this class
is present so it will start from the
package where this class is present and
go further sub classes sub
packages okay so first way is through
atate component
scan and another way is through atate
configuration so spring boot also looks
for hey do you have any at theate
configuration class present so it will
look for those right and if it found
that one then it will use all those at
theate B which you have
defined and just remember one thing
atate configuration is also a atate
component right so we can see that also
annotation at
theate
configuration so at theate configuration
is nothing also but component itself so
whatever the package you have defined
either you have defined or spring boot
autoc configure has been taken so in
that package it also looks for at theate
configuration class and once it find the
at theate configuration
class it uses these beans also so
whatever the bean method you have
provided it will also collect it and
create a bean for those so these are the
two ways at theate component scan and at
theate configuration spring boot finds
the classes for which Bean has to be
creation
created and the second one is at what
time these beans get created at what
time these beans get created so the
answer should be like in two ways the
first one
is eager
initialization eager initialization
means at the time we start our
application that only that at that time
itself beans get
created another answer is
lazy not at the time of uh application
startup but whenever it is actually
needed only that time it is created so
there are two ways or you can say that
two time this be get
created so there are certain called
scope I will cover it in the next part
like there are different types of scope
single turn scope prototype scope right
so just for now you need to uh
understand that what is eagerness
so just wanted to tell you that beans
with single turn Scopes are eagerly
initialized right so don't worry about
hey what is singlet turnon scope we will
cover in depth later but for now you
have to focus on this eagerness or lazy
part just say that this is just an
example that single turn scope beans are
eagly initialized means at the time of
application
startup similarly uh beans with the
Scopes like prototype they are lazy
lazily
initialized right means they are
initialized when they actually not need
it not at the time of
application or another way is that even
though it's a single turn but if you
have used a specifically tell and uh
springboard that at the rate lazy means
you have to initialize it
lazily right so here if you see that I
haven't provide anything at the rate
scope
whether value is like your prototype or
single turn if you haven't provideed
anything by default it's single turn we
will see later in depth but just for
this I haven't provide anything at the
rate scope means by default spring boot
do autoconfigure and it will considered
as single turn but now specifically I
have used this annotation at theate lazy
and telling springboard that hey don't
create this object of this at the time
of application startup whenever it is
required then only create
it so these are the two ways through
which beans get
created you will get better
understanding now with this life cycle
of being and most of things will get
clear cleared because I will tell you
with an example also with
demo so now here this is the life cycle
of a being so first time when you create
an start an application
so when you start an application what
internally springboard will do it will
also invoke the ioc inv verion of
control now ioc what it will do is it
will scan for the Bean search for the
bean and how it will search for the Bean
two ways through at theate component
scan and atate configuration so it will
use this to and look for all the beans
it has to
create and after that it will construct
the bean like if it is
eagerly has to be initialized it will
create it if some beans wanted or
required even though it is lazy it will
invoke it right so at this third step it
will construct the beans which is
required fourth step
is inject dependency into the
constructed beans for example this is an
object user
and there is another class
order okay so now let's say that uh this
user has dependency on this order class
order object so this user needs this
order and let's say this is even lazy
initialized or
something now first third step was
construct a bean so now let's say that
this is singl turn means it can be
eagerly initialized so what it will do
is ioc will create an object of it so
user object is created user object is
created mean user Bean is created which
ioc is
managing now fourth step was inject
dependency into the constructed Bean so
whatever the bean is constructed now
we'll inject that dependency so this
user Bean has dependency on order so now
what it will do is it will create the
order object and injected here injected
here so this is done at the fourth
step fifth step is that now your bean is
fully constructed it was created and
after the dependencies also get injected
into it now it is ready to use before it
ready to use if you have to perform any
task you can use at the post
construct now ultimately Bean is into
action you can use it you can use it to
call its method method you can use it in
your
application now finally Bean is about to
destroy and if you have to perform any
task before it actually get destroyed
you can write it here and ultimately
Bean got
destroyed okay so we will see it one by
one like step one when you are starting
an
application okay so now let's say that
when you are starting an
application so during I told you that
during application startup what springb
will do it will invoke ioc so here I
have taken a locks here so when you
start a spring boot application you will
see this two
lines embedded web application context
initializing spring embedded web
application context initialization
completed this is nothing but the ioc
this is application context right this
is the implementation of ioc Logics what
ioc does we say that ioc manage all the
beans so that application context does
it so now when you start an application
here if you can uh see that it has
initialized the ioc and ioc work is to
First
scan the beans through at theate
component scan annotation it will look
for it and also at theate
configuration it will scan all the beans
and we'll try to construct it so at the
step one during application startup
spring boot invokes ioc container here
application context provide the
implementation for ioc now ioc container
make use of at theate configuration and
at theate component scan to look out for
the classes for B Be need to be
created your step two is construct the
beans right so just see this example I
have created a simple class user and
just default Constructor and just
printing initializing user
now here if you see that I have put at
theate component means I am telling
spring boot to create its
object and also you will see that I
haven't provided anything at the rate
scope means by default what would be the
scope for this class single
turn if it is single turn then means it
is eligible for eager initialization or
eager initialization means during
application startup itself ioc will
create its object create is beam so here
if you see that I started the
server ioc got involved when ioc got
invoke it does atate component scan and
atate configuration it is able to find
this class now it will see that creating
its object default instructor is
called initializing user so it created
The Bean of
this okay so second step is once you
start an application ioc started look
for the bean and it will construct the
bean of those classes which can be
eagerly initialize like single
turn so once the bean is created the The
Next Step would be your bean is created
The Next Step would be dependency
injection so see this one see this
example so I have created a very simple
class user
and it's Constructor initializing user
system.
Prine right and I have put at theate
component here means spring has to
create its object and also there is no
at theate scope means it's single turn
applicable for eager
initialization and I have put one now
dependency that hey user is depend on
this order
right now here if you see that I have
created an order class very simple class
one Constructor default Constructor with
like initializing
order also I have put at theate
component means the spring Bo has to
create its object and if you see there
is no at theate scope means this a
single turn eligible for eager
initialization but now I have
specifically put at the rate lazy means
I'm telling spring boot not to create
its object at the time of application
startup so now what would happen so this
is very basic class I have created now I
have started the
application when I started the
application ioc initialize it will look
for the beans it find this Bean user
bean and it will find these classes user
class where at theate component is there
it will also find order class at theate
component is there now it will see that
hey your order class is marked as lazy
initialized so I don't have to
initialize is during application startup
only when it is needed I have to create
it
so your iOS will try to create first its
object user so it will call initialize
user
done now after
the bean is constructed what it will do
next step is try to inject the
dependency so now it will look that hey
this annotation at theate Auto so it
will with this annotation what is spring
board says that hey is this Bean already
present in container in ioc container
does order Bean is already present if
yes it will just inject it and we can
use
it if no then what would do is ioc Will
first create
order Bean means it will first create
order
object right and then inject into this
So currently order object is not even
constructed right so means ioc will have
to now create first order
object so means this is required so it
will it Constructor will get invoked
initializing
order now it will inject into it now the
order object which is constructed now it
is getting initialized
here
okay but if this is not
present if this dependency is not
present let's say this is not present
and then you start an application you
will see that okay user is initialized
right and there is no dependency you
won't find this you won't find this why
because at application startup this is
marked as lazy order so it will not be
initialized at the time only when it is
needed since we have put a dependency
here in the user means it is needed for
the user Bean so that's why order object
is also
initialized okay but this step is clear
right after the construction of the bean
dependency injection
happens through the help
of
Auto
so there is uh another thing that there
are different ways of doing an injection
construction injection Setter injection
field injection we will cover each
injection in depth in the next part with
the scope I will cover this uh
dependency injection also but you
already know dependency injection right
uh it uses this atate autoi anotation so
first it will check if Bean is already
present use it don't create new Bean of
this if Bean is not found then only
spring will create it and inject it so
this injection there are three logic
which we will see
later okay now your user object is now
fully constructed now it is ready to use
but before ready to use if any pre task
you have to do you can do through at the
rate post construct annotation so here
very simple user class marked as atate
component again like previously it has
dependence an
order this is a sample base Constructor
initializing user but now I have written
this class which is marked as atate post
construct and you can give any name and
I've just printed that bean has been
constructed and dependencies has been
injected to only after that this will
get
involved now if you start the
application ioc started ioc able to find
this class that it has to create its
object and it is single turn eligible
for uh eager initialization so it will
create initializing user it will call
its
Constructor after that it will inject
look for any dependency injection so
Auto wired it it has dependency on order
order Bean is present let's say no so it
will invoke the order so order like
initializing order and will update it
now your bean is ready after that it
will invoke at theate post constru
so now it will print
this okay so that's the
sequence so you can do any uh pre-task
like if you want to do any logging you
can do it here or if you want to
initialize something you can do it here
like any map hash map something you want
to put anything some data you can
initialize it here before using
it now at fifth step you can say that
the bean actually you use start using it
so in this step I'm talking about uh
post construct happen now actually you
are actually using the bean so you now
you have a user object let's say now
you're calling that user object do some
method you are actually using it in your
application that's what I mean use the
bean now once the bean has been
constructed also now it's time for is to
get destroyed but before it getting
destroyed you have to do some pre-task
like okay before it actually destroyed I
have to release all the resources so you
can use this atate P destroy annotation
so before the bean actually get
destroyed this method will get invoked
let's say you have a DB connection and
you before Bean get destroyed you have
to make sure that yes DB connection is
uh released no resources uh hold so you
can check it in
this so now again if you see that very
simple class user no dependencies is
there
right at theate post construct pre
destroy have
written now when you start an
application generally this is the main
class which is present into this when
you start an
application your ioc started right so
this is also you will get a context
object ioc application context object
right so here I'm catching it and
specifically closing
it right I am specifically closing it
generally you don't have to close all
right so but I here for the testing
purpose to show you I'm specifically
closing it so what would be the flow
when I start this application first ioc
will start when ioc will start so it's
running right when ioc will start it
will find this Bean it's a single turn
eagerly initialize eligible so it will
initialize the user then it look for any
dependency no dependency means now
object is fully constructed user now it
will do Post construct so post
Constructor initiated will get
printed now you can uh so this one
happen so now your object is ready to
use but as soon as it ready to use we
are now closing it the next step so now
when we are closing the application
context means when we are closing the
container all the beans which are
present inside this will also get
destroyed so it will call for Speed
destroy method on those beans right in
each classes if you have any uh pre
destroy so that would get invoke for
each Bean right in a specific classes
beans so now Bean is about to destroy
and pre- Destroy method for this user
Bean so this will get involved Bean is
about to destroy and pre destroy method
and ultimately your ioc will get
closed
okay so we have covered till this all
your whole life cycle of a bean is get
completed also I hope that clarifies you
a lot at what time Bean get created what
actually Bean is and but the next topic
we will cover is your dependency
injection Auto we have already seen what
it does but different type of injection
we have to see very important right
construction injection very important we
used a lot like in the industry and the
scope of the be
Bean very important
too right so this is one more property
which I will cover that qualifier when
you have more than one bean for the same
typ that I told you right if you have
more than one bean for this user user
user which which Bean to use in your
code you bean name and qualifier help
you to choose that I want to use this
object so this three part I will cover
next okay team if you have any doubt in
this this is very important topic in the
life cycle part eagerness lazy
initialized part right and do try it out
with your hands like uh then only you
will get more questions and then we can
discuss further okay guys thank you see
you soon